- Hey folks, and welcome to
the learn UI design lesson
on starting a new UI design project.
So in this video, what
I wanna do is give you
a four-step process for
beginning any UI design project,
and sure different projects
are gonna have different
processes, absolutely.
But I wanna give you
kinda a general outline
that you can follow, whether
you're doing say just a single
page homework assignment for this course,
or you're doing a multi-year project
with your employer, doesn't matter.
You take the same four-step process,
dial it up if you need,
dial it back if you need,
but you kinda have an
outline of how to proceed
as soon as you know
you're gonna start working
on something new.
So let's dive right in.
First, I'm gonna review
this four-step process.
Talk a little bit about
each of these steps in turn
but then we're gonna
look at a couple examples
where we apply it and see
kinda how things play out.
The first step anytime you start
a new UI project is to determine
your brand and your goals.
And by brand, all I mean
is what you want your users
to feel about you.
Should your users feel that
you're really authoritative and official,
or should they feel that you're
like friendly and casual,
or that you're kind of buttoned up
and just whatever
adjectives they would use
or short phrases they
would use to describe you.
That's your brand.
It's as simple as that.
Likewise goals is anything
that you just want your users to do.
Maybe you want 10% of
people visiting this page
to sign up for your mailing list,
or maybe you want your page
to be accessible to users
with screen readers.
We'll talk about a couple
of different types of goals
that you can have in just a moment.
But overall, the important thing is right
when you get going on a new project,
figure out what you want your brand to be.
This is especially critical
for you doing the UI design work,
and then also figure out
what goals you want to hit.
What determines if a
project is successful.
Next, you're gonna collect
and compile inspiration.
And this step has a lot of wiggle room
depending on just how big your project is.
If you're a pretty experienced designer
and you're working alone,
maybe you're just doing a
side project or something.
You may not actually really
compile any inspiration
specifically at the start,
but especially if you're
more of a beginning designer
or you're working with a larger team,
you just wanna be really clear about
what's inspiring you and why,
and what's influencing you and why.
And this is something that you'll be
very conscientious about.
Now, there's actually
a whole separate video
just on this step.
So I'm kinda gonna gloss
over it in this video.
The third step is to sketch and wireframe,
and like the second step,
how much you sketch and
how much you wireframe
really depends on the
complexity of your project.
If you're working on
something, say like a blog,
you may not do much wireframing at all.
Just kinda quickly sketch out.
Yep, title's gonna be the top,
post is gonna be below that,
the author's name might go here,
but you can pretty
quickly get to the details
of the visual design.
With a more complex
and interactive project
the process of wireframing overall
might also include researching your users,
iterating on low fidelity designs,
maybe usability testing some
of your designs, et cetera.
All before doing the visual design work
to make those designs look great.
For the purposes of this course,
I'm just gonna assume that you
have a sketched out version
of the interface, ready to go.
If you are interested in
how you get to that step
and how you make usable designs,
I have a whole other course on
that called learn UX design.
And that covers the wireframing,
the usability testing,
the user research, et cetera.
But for now, we're gonna
presume we have a sketch
that's ready to go.
And we're just gonna be
focusing on the visual design.
And then the fourth step is
to explore visual styles.
And so there's kinda this connection
between the first step
and the fourth step,
because what you determined as your goals
and your brand actually affects
what visual styles you're gonna
start to play around with.
When you get specific
about what your brand is,
that affects everything
in your visual style,
your colors, your typography,
the illustrations,
or the photography, or
the icons that you use.
Even the tone of voice that
the text on your site is in.
So this step is really just about
starting to explore little snippets to UI,
pieces of text or buttons or UI controls
or common repeating elements.
And as an official deliverable,
this is often called style tiles.
So at the highest level,
that's how you start a new project.
First, you determine the brand and goals.
You collect some inspiration,
you sketch out the general
overview of the screens,
and then you start filling in details,
exploring different fonts, colors,
UI components, et cetera.
Now let's take these ideas
and start looking at a sample project.
So here's a short brief for a
project called Genius Notes,
which is actually something
that I worked on just a bit ago.
My client Danny came
to me and talked about
wanting to create high
quality written guides
that basically take a
whole variety of skills,
and teach you the very best
way to learn those skills.
The way he described it,
which really kinda hit it
home for me is he said,
have you ever learned some skill?
And when you were a beginner
you had no idea what book
you should be reading,
what teacher you should be
listening to, et cetera.
And then once you kinda
get into that world,
you realize that almost
everyone who's really good,
kinda respects the same
couple of resources.
And he's like, we just wanna
recommend those resources
for every single skill.
The monetization would be
through affiliate links
of recommendations for
different products and services,
and Danny stress that the affiliate deals
are not gonna really influence
which recommendation is picked.
So it's all neutral.
The whole concept is this
site will build your trust
by recommending the very best resources.
And if they happen to make some money
from that, that's awesome.
All right, so step number
one is really picking
what goals does our design need to achieve
and what does success look like here?
So one of the first things to focus on
with goals is how the site makes money
and how the site makes
money is gonna be tied
into what the design is.
So for instance, if this
site is making money
through affiliate links and
affiliate recommendations,
then the recommendations
need to be front and center.
But that's kind of a short term fix
because on the other hand,
the recommendations
also need to be trusted.
If the site doesn't earn your trust over,
it doesn't matter how front and center
the recommendations are.
No one's gonna buy them anyways.
Now, goals related to how a
site makes money are one thing,
you'll also see kind of behavioral goals.
Do we want people to download something
or subscribe to something,
purchase something, donate,
maybe use a new feature, whatever.
I have a whole bunch of behavioral goals
listed on the starting a project
cheat sheet attached below.
For the purposes of this project,
just saying that we really
want the recommendations
to be front and center and
have people buying them.
That's kind of all we
can do for right now.
There's also user experience goals.
For instance, we might
have different devices
that we want this to work on.
So in this case, this is
gonna be a responsive website,
meaning it needs to work across bubbles,
tablets, desktops, whatever.
Sometimes I'll also throw in something
about users must find the
app simple and usable,
or easy to use or whatever.
But for a site that's
comprised mostly of articles
that doesn't really strike
me as quite as important.
And then one other type of
goal that's important to list
is context schools.
So in this case, you know,
like what's the context
of the user,
the user in this case is
mostly gonna be finding
articles via Google.
So everything essential about the site
does need to be conveyed
via the guide pages
rather than say like the
Homepage or the About page.
So I'll just put guide page
must convey all necessary
information to new users.
Perfect, and even though
this is just kind of a rough
stab at things,
this is actually decently similar
to the list that we came up with.
And listing goals, just like this
even if it's like a little
bit of a rough draft
is a couple things here.
First of all, listing your goals makes you
more likely to achieve them, right?
If you don't know your goals,
you're really only gonna be
hitting them on accident.
But beyond that, if you're
working with a client
or an employer,
when you show that you are laser focused
on taking their business goals
and translating them into a website
and then meeting those goals,
you're making your client
trust your judgment here.
And I'll also talk about this a lot more
in the getting good design feedback
and presenting your designs lesson,
but you're making your future
design reviews a lot easier,
because presenting your design
based on how it meets the goals
you laid out in the beginning
is the single best way to
structure a design review.
And it will get you way better feedback
if you do that.
Now I'll just say for like
really small projects,
like learn UI design homework assignment,
or maybe you do some sort of
hundred days of UI exercise.
You don't really need to worry
too much about these goals.
Instead for that, what I
would do is just jot down
a couple notes on brand that
you're trying to achieve,
and just leave it there.
And so, yeah, let's use
that as a transition
to talking about brand here.
When I say brand that
might sound like something
that's kinda handwavy or a
little artsy and mysterious,
I really don't mean for it to be,
brand is simply what you want
your users to perceive you as,
and it's as simple as coming up
with just a list of adjectives, right?
And so when I was working with my client
for this particular site,
I started asking him questions,
trying to really get a handle on
what kind of brand he was going for.
I said, hey, what are like
similar sites that you
kinda look up to or think
are doing something right
that you also want to do right?
The very first thing he
said was the Wirecutter.
And the Wirecutter is
a recommendation site.
It's known for just being
ridiculously thorough.
This is an article on
"The Best Robot Vacuums."
It is 17,000 words long.
And they test, you know, I don't know,
perhaps dozens of vacuums.
They spend scores of hours doing this
and they write a small
novel of a report on
which one they thought was the best,
which, okay, that's the Roomba.
Great, now you know.
So we talked about the Wirecutter
and why that was so awesome.
And we started coming up
with little phrases like
it earns your trust, or
it's slightly obsessive.
It's also balanced,
you know, they're not playing favorites.
They actually wanna get to
the bottom of what's the best.
Another thing that Danny was inspired by
was the Amazon Kindle logo, right?
Here's just this boy
sitting on a small hill
and the starry night,
very small hill in the starry night,
just reading his Kindle.
And it's kind of reflected
in some of these screenshot images.
You've got like the beautiful
bookstore vibe going on
on the screen itself,
but then it's surrounded
by this just serene,
nighttime landscape.
And there's just a little bit
of sense of wonder in that.
Now sometimes sites are
gonna be not even close
to being competitors to the
thing that you want to do,
but they inspire you
along some other access
that you just can't ignore.
So Wait But Why, this
was awesome for Danny
because it embraced its
own geekiness in his words.
Here's a giant article
on "The Fermi Paradox"
which is about why we haven't
found aliens in the universe.
If you've never been to Wait But Why
it's a bit of a silly blog.
There's a lot of like hand drawn,
stick, figure images and stuff.
The writing is really, really casual,
but just goes into
incredible depth, right?
I mean, you can see this is also
an extremely long article.
So that was something
that we also wanted to do.
Another way to kinda determine your brand
is to start asking yourself,
what do you not?
Like what would,
if your users thought X about you,
what would be a failure?
And so that started to
generate some more ideas,
preaching or boasting, right?
Genius Notes shouldn't be big.
It shouldn't be spammy.
It shouldn't be inhumane
or sloppy,
et cetera.
Now, one thing that's
interesting about these
is they can actually start to generate.
If you take the opposite of them,
they can start to kind of
generate more adjectives
of what you're going for.
So we're humble,
not boasting.
Or we are considered
not spammy.
Or we're precise, not sloppy.
And it's as simple as this,
I've got a couple other brand questions
in the starting a project cheat sheet,
just things to kinda get you thinking
and generating this
little list of adjectives.
Now from this list, Danny said,
here's the ones that are kind of the most
important trustworthy, right?
So that came from earning your trust.
We talked about that a bunch,
geeky talked about that,
embracing your own geekiness.
Humble
and balanced.
And it really only took us
not even two hours to get to this point,
but already, this is really exciting to me
and my designer senses like
already coming up with ideas
of how I'm gonna try and
convey this trustworthiness
or this geekiness or the humility,
you know, using little pieces of interface
or fonts or colors or whatever it is.
Now, my goal in this video
is to also kind of kickstart
your designer sense
into starting to translate adjectives
like this into interfaces.
Whenever you're determining your brand.
I really wanna hit home
that there's two things
that you should always be doing,
the first picking those adjectives
or short phrases, right?
Trustworthy or touch a wonderment
because the big secret here
is that a lot of the seeming
subjectiveness of UI design
fades away when you specify what you want
your users to feel,
and then you design to those ideas.
Like for instance,
we want a Genius Notes to be trustworthy,
but what's a trustworthy font?
Well, I think you already
have some idea of this.
So I wanna show you something
that you've probably
never seen before.
This is "The New England
Journal of Medicine"
where every single font on the site
is replaced with Comic Sans.
And as you scroll through this,
it's like really difficult
even to take it seriously.
I even find it tough to view
it as a completed design.
Like it looks a little bit
kinda just like a wireframe
and in large part that's
because Comic Sans
is not a font that inspires trust.
But if I go and I remove
that single line of code
that replaced all fonts with that,
all of a sudden things
look a lot different.
It just looks a lot more considered
and professional and trustworthy,
and the feel of it totally changes
just with the topography alone.
Now that's kind of an extreme example,
but that's the sort of thing
that we're gonna be
applying to everything.
All right, and the second
part of determining your brand
really has to do with picking
the opposite qualities
that you want to convey.
But what can be really good
is not to pick some straw man.
Oh, you know, we don't want
to be bad customer service.
We wanna be good customer service.
That's not really a brand value.
The very best brand values
have defensible opposites.
For instance, scrappy
is a great brand value
because the opposite of
scrappy is like authoritative
and official and trustworthy.
And that's a perfectly reasonable thing
that a site or a brand might aspire to.
Now to be clear, some of
the things we've chosen
have opposites, right?
We wanna be humble, not boasting,
but if we were trying to make boasting
a little more defensible,
we might say, we don't wanna be humble.
We wanna be humble.
We don't wanna be omnipotent or something.
Like you could imagine
a site which has written
where the tone of voice is just very wise
and almost omnipotent.
No, we want to avoid that.
Or balanced, we wanna
be balanced rather than
the opposite of balanced
isn't just biased, right?
That's not a very positive thing.
We might say,
we wanna be balanced rather than loyal.
Loyal sounds like a positive thing,
but in this case, it's
what we want to avoid.
And if we start sounding loyal,
we know we're kind of getting
away from our brand values.
I can actually kinda just
put these up here, right?
Trustworthy rather than say casual,
maybe the more defensible
version of untrustworthy.
It just has a different
value than inspiring trust.
For geeky, I don't really
know of a defensible opposite,
but you know, in this case,
let's say geeky rather than bored,
even though bored isn't really defensible.
I would still say that if we ever come
across sounding bored,
when designing the site
or writing the site,
we know we're getting away
from our brand values.
Humble, we already talked about.
And same thing with balanced.
So we can say, okay, cool,
we're done with step one.
Now we're gonna move towards
collecting and compiling
some inspiration, which actually,
if you were paying attention,
we were starting to do that.
When I asked my client,
hey, what are the sites that inspire you?
Even if it's in a totally different field
or doing a totally different thing,
where do you kinda draw inspiration from
that's starting to get
at the heart of step two.
Now again, there's a whole
other video that explores this
in a lot more detail.
Then it would be time
to sketch and wireframe
out a little bit.
But honestly, with
something as straightforward
as an article recommending a product,
I'm probably not gonna take the time to do
two in depth the sketches.
Instead, I'm gonna start
exploring visual styles.
So step one and step four are really
where we're going to be
spending most of our time
in this video.
All right, so we've got
this brand trustworthy,
geeky, humble, balanced.
It's a recommendation site.
We're trying to give these really
high quality recommendations.
Let's start with topography, right?
Let's start trying to distill
these brand values into typography.
And that's actually a really
a fantastic place to start
for a site that's mostly
made of articles anyways.
So what fonts, when you
think of trustworthy,
when you think of trustworthy,
what fonts do you think of,
or even what general category of fonts?
You don't really have to know too much.
I realized this video is in
the beginning of the course.
So don't fret, if you're
like, I've got no idea,
but the thing I'm thinking of is serif.
Serif fonts just tend to
look a little more detailed,
considered official, classy,
old, wizened, whatever.
When I think a trustworthy,
I think of serif fonts.
And so I'm gonna do something like
come to my Good Fonts Table,
which is a resource in the fourth unit,
the topography unit,
I'm gonna filter by serifs
and I'm start going through this list.
I'm gonna find ones that
I think might be worth
kinda playing around with.
So I actually went and stole these fonts
from the file that I was designing.
And because these are the
actual ones I looked at.
So here's FreightText Pro
that's in my good fonts list.
This is Freight Display,
which is really similar.
It's in the same family.
Merriweather is another one on the list,
Meta Serif on the list,
More Pro, PT Serif,
Tisa Pro.
So all of these are on the list.
I'm just looking at my own list of fonts,
kind of the best of my own past judgment.
Just filtering down into a couple
of different starting points.
And maybe you have some
idea of what you think looks
the most trustworthy here.
Maybe you don't, either
way it's really fine.
The whole point of this exploring visual
style step is just to
get some stuff out there
and start mixing and matching
and seeing what feels right.
Now recall that our other big
value here was geeky, right?
What fonts are geeky?
Well, again, I'm gonna go back
to my Good Fonts Table here.
Maybe monospaced fonts are geeky, right?
Because they kind of remind you of say,
typing into a computer terminal
or something like that, coding.
So over here,
I just copied a couple possible bylines.
Each of these are in the monospaced fonts,
Fira Mono, Inconsolata, Input Mono.
Of these, I think Input is
kinda my favorite, right?
And when I start to look
at these letter forms,
and by the way, I mean, we're
gonna get way more into this
in the topography unit,
but I just wanna make it so clear that
when this seems like something
that's really subjective
and loosey goosey, our whole process
for figuring out what font to use
is listing a bunch of adjectives
that match what we want our users to feel,
and then trying to match
those adjectives to fonts.
And when we're matching
the adjectives to fonts,
we're like looking at the
shapes of letters here.
I love that the letters here
are so squared off, right.
That just makes it feel
particularly geeky.
And you know, it's happening
to some degree with these,
but this one is by far
the most pronounced.
And so maybe I'll take that
as a jumping off point.
And I'll say, what other
fonts kinda exhibit
some of that squared off nature.
Right, I can go here.
Let's cancel the Mono filter,
but let's just search square.
Yeah, squared.
Okay, cool.
And already I see.
Oh, I've got Clear Sans on this list.
Alright, well, Clear Sans.
Let's throw that one in here too.
And
another one we had was DIN 2014
that one's on Adobe Fonts.
Perfect.
Another thing I can do here is
when I'm just kind of messing
around with little styles
and trying to find a font,
I will put them in uppercase,
exploring uppercases
is an important part
of choosing your font.
We talk about that in the topography unit.
But now I've started compiling
a bunch of ideas here
and I could start to mix
and match a title font
with a little byline font
right here and figure out
what's gonna look the best.
What do I like, what don't I like?
Now in a second, I'm gonna
have you pause the video.
So actually get your finger
ready to press the space bar
or pause button or whatever.
I want you to open up the Good
Fonts Table in another tab.
I want you to open up
your design app of choice,
and I want you to take a stab
at kind of designing just
a trustworthy yet geeky
title mixed with a byline.
You can throw in a first
paragraph of body text, too
if you're feeling really ambitious.
You can use one of the
fonts that I've listed here.
You can use a different one.
I recommend using the Good Fonts Table,
unless you have a strong sense
of other fonts that you like
and feel trustworthy or geeky.
But go ahead, pause.
Do that little exercise and
we will see you in just a sec.
All right, welcome back.
Now I wanna show you the
fonts that I picked for this,
but the way I'm gonna show you
is I'm actually just going
to give you the presentation.
A very brief version of the presentation
that I gave to my client.
This was kind of my first
stab at putting together
some UI that met all the brand
values we had established.
So the whole way this
presentation was structured
is I put our mission at the top,
make accessible the best
way to learn any given skill
and below that each of the
four main brand values.
Then whatever I've put on this screen
that this slide is talking about.
I've highlighted the brand
value that it most relates to.
So in this case,
the article title,
"How to Learn Yoga: The
Best Way for Most People."
One thing we had talked about was that
Genius Notes should really
give kind of the middle
of the road way,
that's gonna be most
effective for most people.
Well, that's balanced.
Awesome.
And it's also making
accessible the best way
to learn a given skill.
Now we change the font, right?
So here's this font Freight
from the Good Fonts Table.
That's the one I went with.
And Freight in particular
is really trustworthy.
It's finely crafted letters reflect
the careful recommendations
in each Genius Notes guide.
Then we've got a little
byline going on here.
We'll pair Freight with a techy,
squared off terminal inspired font.
This one is Plex.
I didn't show you Plex just a minute ago,
but this is also in the Good Fonts Table.
And yes, it's geeky.
Another thing, and this doesn't pertain
as much to the UI design
that we're gonna cover in this course,
but the copy really can
affect the brand too.
If someone sees how recent this was,
which it was recent when
I gave the presentation,
that's kind of a real cool
sign that actually this site
does care about its guides
and tries to keep them up-to-date.
That's trustworthy.
So there's a number of
things that I call out
in this presentation that are about
how I say something or what
the page actually says,
the copy, the text on the page.
This happens to be calling
out just how impressive
the teacher's little resume is here.
And by the way,
when I talk about doing a style tile,
this is the sort of thing I'm saying.
I've taken a couple different font styles,
the headline font style,
a little byline piece here,
a little author bio, an author photo,
and I've combined them all together
in the way that they would
be displayed on the site.
So if you're working with clients
and looking for kind of
an in-between deliverable
after you've established
your brand and your goals,
but before you're actually
designing out the whole UI,
show them a couple of
style tiles like this,
just say, how do we feel
about this direction?
I'll keep going here.
You can read the text if you want,
but it's a little bit more
about the actual text here.
And then of course we put
in some high quality imagery
with people doing yoga,
and then we start to scroll down.
This is, as we get into the article
and my call outs here are
about all sorts of aspects
of the design.
We've got the top learning
resource, the what?
Well, and then we're
using this as a little
chance to explain a bit more
about how the site works.
Again, the users are coming from Google.
We can't rely on them
having seen the About page
or the Homepage.
So we have to explain this sort of stuff
in the article itself.
And I'm just trying to give my client
the sense that everything I've done here,
it's all precise and it's all goal-based.
We scroll on a bit more,
the same sort of thing
is going on, et cetera.
And at that point, the
presentation comes to an end.
How does it end?
It doesn't end with me
presenting 10 other concepts
or anything else like that.
It's just above.
Here's what I designed.
Here's how it meets our goals.
How are we succeeding at those standards?
How are we failing?
And how do we move forward?
In this project ended up
going extremely smoothly
in large part because
I just kept the design
so focused on what the goals were.
Also, if you were one step ahead of me,
the entire way you may have said,
if your brand value is humility,
why the heck is your name Genius Notes?
We recognize that too.
And by the end of the project,
the site had changed to the name, Guidery.
Guidery had incredibly
long form articles here,
a Homepage,
simple, clean to the point, trustworthy.
even the About page felt very
considered and carefully done.
Okay, so at this point
you might be wondering
there's so many brand adjectives.
What do I have to do?
Learn how to translate
every single brand adjective
into different typographic styles
and colors and imagery
styles and whatever.
No, you do not.
There's really, there is
an 80/20 rule at play here,
which is to say an 80/20
rule is when 80% of the work
comes from 20% of the effort,
or 80% of the output comes
from 20% of the input.
In our case,
what I want to have you do is master
the 20% of possible brand adjectives
or brand values that you
will see 80% of the time.
So without further ado,
let's talk about the five most common
brands that you're gonna see.
And I'm just gonna do a quick rundown
on how they influence
typography, color, imagery,
but really don't have to worry too much
about the details right now.
I just want you to get
familiar with these five brands
and kind of start to
recognize when you see them,
and notice the patterns
of what's happening
when good designers designed
to meet these brand values.
The first one is clean and simple,
and that is by far the
most common client requests
that I've had.
Hey, we just want something
that's clean and simple,
neat and modern.
Typography for clean and
simple is often gonna be
sans-serif fonts in
particular Grotesque sans.
If you know what that means, great.
If you don't do not worry about it,
we'll get to it later.
Likewise, with coloring
this the primary palette,
all you need to know is there's bright,
clean, primary, hues.
You know, it's like the
four pack of crayons
you get when you go to a restaurant
and your toddler wants
to color on the menu,
or you'll see monohue schemes
where the whole site
basically just has one
main theme color.
And the variations of that
theme color are hues throughout.
We'll get to all this in the color unit.
The imagery might be
illustrations or photos.
Now the next most common brand.
And I don't know if this
is maybe second by rank,
but it's certainly pretty
easy to know when you see it
is fancy, luxury kind of formal brands.
They might use serif fonts
and they're much more likely
to have a pallet of gray scale,
maybe there's gold accents or something.
And if there's any photography,
it's gonna be extremely high quality,
very beautiful stuff.
Then there's also friendly sites.
This is just the sites that
you load them up and you're like, wow,
this site is very casual.
It's just, it's very friendly.
It's cheaper, feels nice.
They're almost always gonna
be using sans-serifs fonts
of some sort or another.
And again, we'll get to the color unit
exactly what these mean.
With a friendly site, sometimes
you might see some like
cute little illustrations
or something like that.
Probably not something you're gonna see
on a really fancy site,
or if it's done, it's gonna be done
in a very different style.
Quirky, this one might
be the least common brand
that your clients will have you do.
But a lot of designers get
interested in doing this
themselves as they see kind
of all these other projects
that fit in these other buckets.
And quirky, sometimes they're
gonna have maybe quirky
or fonts or more of a muted palette,
more likely to have an orangish-red
than a pinkish-red, for instance.
And if there's illustrations,
they might kind of further
enhance the quirkiness.
So we'll get into some examples in a sec.
And then the final one is
I'm just calling a techie,
anything that's technical
or scientific or futuristic.
We talked about squared off sans-serifs
being kinda geeky, that would
fit very much in this vibe.
Talked about monospace,
you'd also see plenty of uppercase.
And so on.
This also has different connotations
for what you'd see in the
color and the imagery.
Now, if you're watching this on your toes,
you might be thinking,
wait a second, Eric,
you just showed us this example
where we had a serif font.
And yeah, it was kinda going for this,
like not really fancy, not luxury,
but like trustworthy vibe.
And it kinda feels like
it matches this row.
And yet at the same time,
we also had some techie aspects, right?
We're going for that
squared-off sans-serifs font
was kind of a vibrant orange.
Can there really be two
of these at the same time?
Or does it just count as clean and simple?
How do they all fit together?
Okay, here's your answer.
Here's how it all fits together.
This might be one of the most egregious
simplifications in the entire course,
but bear with me.
I have smashed the four
most common brand adjectives
into one chart.
And these sites you might recognize
as the reference sites from the building
your gut instinct lesson,
except now they're on a two by two grid.
So the whole idea here is
if you wanna see a site
that's really fancy,
you look towards the top,
for instance, semplice.com.
Cool, I can just open this link.
I guarantee you, I did not
make the table on purpose,
but we are definitely looking
at a gray scale, gold accent,
serif font, high quality, very classy,
formal looking site.
On the other sides of the spectrum.
If we wanted to see something
that was maybe a little more
quirky kind of way down here,
we could look at a site like Abstract
and sure enough Abstract
is a little bit quirky.
It's got these kind of
gratuitous button animations
and this font,
which even though it's
technically a serif font,
it just does not feel very formal.
It's a little more playful and wild.
On the friendly side of the spectrum
we could rail it all the way on this end.
And we could look at
the site for Zeda Labs.
And Zeda labs has a much softer,
kind of a rounded off font here.
They've got playful
animations of their employees
shooting each other with lasers.
They actually say the word shut up
and take my money on a
site that sells something
and so on.
They also tell you that
designers should be focused
on your business goals,
which, hey, Zeda you are
preaching to the choir.
So that's really the friendly
side of the spectrum.
And then finally,
what's all the way on the techie side,
the science authoritative futuristic side.
Origin Materials is a
good example of that.
You look, and you see this sans-serif logo
super squared off, black
and white stark photography.
I scroll down, it feels like I'm scrolling
through a blueprint,
still kind of sparse but
neat and clean, et cetera.
You get the idea.
Now the whole premise
of this chart is that
it's actually kind of difficult
to be both fancy and
quirky at the same time.
If you focus too much on
being formal and luxurious,
you're gonna find it very tough
to also be offbeat in a convincing way,
that may not be strictly true.
The best designers might be able
to kinda hit these opposites,
or they might be able to be very techie,
maybe futuristic and
authoritative and yet casual,
but it just doesn't kinda seem right.
So don't treat this chart
as just representing
the exact location where every
one of these sites lives,
and they couldn't be anywhere else.
And this is right in any
difference of opinion is wrong.
Instead kinda treat this as a resource
that's directionally correct.
When you know what brand values
your site is trying to hit.
If any of those kinda lean
in any of these directions,
you can then check out,
you know, everything
that's in that quadrant.
So for instance, with Guidery, I said,
hey, yeah, we have just a
little bit of fanciness.
Not, it's not all the way
up here with Semplice,
but it's maybe down here,
we started clean and simple, right?
Just something that's
very neutral and plain.
And we go a little bit on the fancy side
and we brought it a little
bit out to the techie side,
just 'cause we wanted
something that was geeky
as well as trustworthy.
Well, that puts us in maybe
the range of Quanta Magazine
or Foundation Medicine.
And if we open up
Foundation Medicine site,
you can see there's some
similar elements going on here.
You know, they've got these big,
beautiful serif details.
There's kind of some angularness.
You've got a serif headline
with a little small uppercase, sans-serif,
neat clean label right by it.
Now our labels were below
and they were orange instead of red,
but you can start to see
they're sort of similar elements
throughout these sites.
Likewise, if we look at Quanta Magazine,
wow, it actually has the same exact thing.
It's got a nice big serif headline
and then a little
uppercase san serif label.
And this is the site where,
when I looked at Quanta Magazine
while working on Guidery,
I thought, you know what?
I think I can use orange
as an accent color.
And that's kind of the point.
The idea is not if I'm
designing a site right here
to just totally ape off of
one of these particular sites
that happens to be nearby,
but to use this whole quadrant
as kind of inspiration,
I'm mixing and matching
elements from wherever.
I might see them,
this chart or the
inspiration that we compiled
in step two, wherever.
All right, there's one
other point I wanna make
about this chart,
which by the way, you
can find the link to it
in the resources below.
But the point I wanna make
is this, clean and simple,
that most common thing that clients want
is right here in the middle.
And to get clean and simple,
we're actually gonna focus a
lot of the next unit on that.
We want things to be very aligned.
We want things to be very consistent.
We want generous white space.
That's really, what's gonna give us
that clean and simple feeling,
but you might get to the
point somewhere down the road,
where once you've
mastered clean and simple,
you think that things are
just a little bit boring,
and this chart actually
presents an answer for that.
One of the biggest things you can do
to spice up your designs
once you've already achieved
clean and simple,
and can do that well is to
start trying to figure out
what brand you need to
inject a little bit more of.
And so even if you didn't start a project
by thinking of your brand values,
it can help you course
correct midway through.
So here's an example of a fictional
medical wholesale supply company, right?
And I just wanna point out that
a lot of the design in this
is technically pretty well done.
It's very well aligned.
It looks neat and clean.
It's on a nice grid system.
There's decent white space,
at least considering how much
content I need to display
and how small the screen is.
But honestly, it's a
little bit boring, right?
And so if I was working on this site,
I might think, how do I add
a little more zing here?
How do I add some excitement?
It just looks kind of bland.
Now, if I wasn't familiar
with different brands
being kind of offshoots
from clean and simple
in different directions,
I might not really have a good
idea of where I should go.
But if I know that the
answer is to really get
a good handle on what
brand I'm trying to convey,
then I can sit down with my
client and I can say, hey,
I want you to tell me what
MedDepot is all about.
I want you to tell me who
you are and who you aren't.
And I want you to tell me the
principles that you stand for.
I want you to tell me the principles
you'd be willing to lose money for, right?
I want to know.
And by the way, a lot of
this stuff is in the starting
a project cheat sheet,
these brand reflections.
But you say, I wanna know what you believe
that all your competitors
would disagree with, right?
And say, you start that conversation.
And maybe it takes a while.
Maybe you have to meet a couple times.
Maybe there's some back and forth,
but after a while they get it
and they come back to you and they say,
you know what, Eric?
And I'm just making this up here.
This is just a totally made up example,
but maybe they come in and they say,
what we really stand for is just this idea
of pro recognized pro, right?
Like if you're a doctor,
you're already one of the
smartest people out there.
And you're certainly one
of the hardest working
and you're making life or death
decisions every single day.
While some people are like moving pixels
around the screen, right.
(laughs)
But if you're a doctor
you're like absolutely
a consummate professional
and MedDepot is the company
that wants to stand by them.
And you say, whoa, that's
totally different, right?
If someone can describe
their brand like that,
even like they didn't
just list adjectives,
but you still get a sense of
kind of what they're all about.
And we can start boiling that down
into different design
changes that we wanna make.
So, you know, first of all,
this stock image does this say,
I wanna stand by doctors?
This guy doesn't even look real, right?
Stock photography, we'll talk about this
in the imagery lesson,
but stock photography using good photos
is like a super power in design.
It's the same thing with
using high quality fonts.
Here's something that looks
a lot more real, right?
Like this guy, I don't know
anything about doctors,
but presumably he's like
looking into someone's
chest cavity right now.
And he's wearing Packers
Gear as he does it.
(laughs)
This is not fake.
So let's start by just
trying to get some imagery
that really says, you know
what we see who you are.
We recognize you as a pro.
And we're going to honor that.
All right, now we definitely
need to change this,
text color, let's get this white.
Let's remove about us
'cause that's not a very
good call to action.
It's not about MedDepot, right?
It's about pros coming here,
taking care of their needs
and getting on with their work.
And actually, what if
we took this headline
instead of having 20,000
satisfied customers up there,
which is maybe a little bit cheesy,
what if we just said, helping
20,000 plus professionals
do their best work.
I realized they might not be
selling directly to doctors.
It's a problem with fictional examples.
So a little bit weird.
One other thing we can
do is just like throw on
a black outline on an outline,
but a black layer here with 70% opacity
just makes it a little bit
easier to read this headline.
And maybe while we're at it,
let's actually also change
the font a little bit.
We know if we have this brand,
that's all about like selling
high quality equipment to
well trained professionals.
If you had to take a guess
of whether that leans
fancy, friendly, quirky or techie,
I think I would definitely
say it leans techie, right?
So maybe if I'm gonna change fonts here,
wanna go towards something
that's a little bit more like
a squared off font.
In this case we could play
around with one like Clear Sans.
You might remember that one
from just a little bit earlier.
Let's give it a slightly bigger size.
Talked about this in the text unit,
but headlines don't need to
have very much line spacing.
It's gonna do the same thing
Clear Sans for, not the whole page, right?
But just a lot of this kind
of header and subheader text.
Now, as far as the colors go,
blue is pretty inoffensive.
And so I feel like I could
actually pick something.
Maybe I'd just pick a
color from this image
so I can take this blue and
then go and replace it with,
I think I was seeing something
like 170 was the hue.
Don't worry too much about
this color detail stuff.
We'll get a lot more into it.
Yeah, there we go.
Something like that.
So now it's kind of a
slate green, so to speak.
We might also be able to do
something with the blue too.
If we're gonna have a
squared off font here,
like Clear Sans, you can
just kind of see in this E
it's not like a perfect circle,
this O not even close, right?
Very squared off on the
tops and on the sides.
We're gonna do the same thing
with all our little shapes here.
You can see this bounding box has a nice
four pixel border radius here.
We're gonna take all the stuff,
I'm gonna use a plugin called Simlayer.
And I'm gonna select all the layers
that have the same border radius.
There we go.
Four pixel border radius,
I'm gonna select them all.
And I'm gonna give it just
a one pixel border radius,
just the slightest bit here.
And then all of these things
have kind of this softer
two pixel border.
I'm gonna take a bunch of those
and give them a one pixel border.
I don't think that's
gonna fix it universally.
There's still a couple little things
I'm gonna need to change
individually here.
But now all of a sudden it's just got
kind of a tighter feel to it.
I'm gonna put one more
black kind of scrim layer behind this.
And there we go.
We've taken the colors to
these cooler slate grays,
just feels a little more technical
and kinda almost colder, but
it's also literally the colors
of medical professionals.
We took the font, we made
a little more squared off,
kind of adding a sense of professionality
or preciseness as well.
And that's mirrored in the border radius
and the border width,
and all the little shapes
all around the screen.
And we even made a couple of texts changes
just to kinda back this all up.
And so, all right, fine.
This is, you know, it's a site.
It's great.
But when you compare
to where we came from,
there's so much more attitude.
There's so much, it just looks
like this is a real thing.
It's a lot more compelling.
And that's the power
of knowing your goals,
specifying your brand
and designing to that.
I've said it before in this video.
And I know I will say
it again in this course,
but if you don't specify
what your goals are,
you will only be managing
to hit them on accident.
So whenever you start a new
project, go ahead, figure out,
just jot down a couple adjectives
for what your brand is,
or if there's a specific
goal that you wanna hit,
write those down too.
But designed to those things,
not only will it make your design better
and that should reason
enough alone to do it,
but it will also make your
clients and your employers
and the people you work with love you more
and trust you more
because you're on the same page as them.
And you're trying to bring your design
to not just be some pretty picture
that they can hang on their fridge,
but to be something
that solves the problems
that you all have.
And of course, as we saw,
it's never too late to do a goal focused
or a brand focus to redesign.
And even if you have a
decent existing design,
you can start to think what are the brands
that we're trying to convey?
How do we do this?
It's all a win.
So let me know if you have any questions,
we'll see you in the student community
and check out the homework below.
Cheers!